[SPEAKER_03]: So, if I think about past memories when I was five, ten, twenty, thirty, to my present experience, there's a sense of continuity or self to whom those experiences happened, which also informs thoughts about the future.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I was wondering, could that sense of continuity be one way to describe what bhāva is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, certainly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a form of... well, it's the way you exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Bhakti, that continuity from your past,
[SPEAKER_00]: That you can recollect now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is that continuity perceived?
[SPEAKER_00]: Now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Colors the past with the same owner, but it's actually here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And back when that, you know, ten years ago, when that was here and now, that's where that good sense of continuity, sense of I am, that persists throughout these different experiences, that's where it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where that sense of continuity is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That sense of I am, sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the Buddha wasn't advocating to deny
[SPEAKER_03]: This sense of continuity that he was more seeing... No, sense of continuity is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mistake, though, is the mistake of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the mistake that's, again, perpetuated on the basis of a mind that's not free from greed, aversion, delusion, here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why a person who would have uprooted the ownership, freed the mind from conceiving, from the notion of I am, fully developed anatta,
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha says in the suttas, that person would not think, oh, but I was in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now I'm not, because I'm an arahant, but I was in the past and I... or I would be in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Past and future were equally affected by that same present that has been purified.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he's fully seeing the sense of continuity as contained within that which is discontinuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, it's fully unownable, fully dependent on the existence and operation of the five aggregates, on their presence.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no... because that's the trick with that sense of continuity and the sense of I am, sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels like it's outside of the experience as a whole, as a perpetual entity, owner,
[SPEAKER_01]: To whom these things occur, feelings, perceptions, past, future, but it exists independent of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's changing that order through right contemplation that can only arise on the basis of virtue and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's when then you start to reverse, you start seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not denying.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not denying the sense of I am, you're not denying the sense of that continuous sense of self that you remember since you were a child, but you're just including it within the arisen, presently arisen feeling, presently arisen perception, intention, state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, you're putting it second.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're enclosing it where it should be enclosed, so that that gratuitous sense of
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is something outside, independent of these feelings that come and go, perceptions come and go.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will fade away.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, people, people have the view and the assumption that their sense of self is independent of the experience as a whole, because that's... they're cultivating it through their attitude and through their action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stop cultivating, you stop providing fuel for it, it will fade away, because it's not actually on the outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not actually independent.
[SPEAKER_03]: And Venerable Aniga brought up a sutta relating to this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was wondering if I could... Go on, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, sort of interrogate my interpretation of... yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's Majjhima Naikāya 74.
[SPEAKER_03]: There are three kinds of feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pleasant feeling, painful feeling and neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the occasion when one feels pleasant feeling, one does not feel painful or neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: On that occasion, one feels only pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the occasion when one feels painful feeling, one does not feel pleasant or neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: On that occasion, one feels only painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the occasion when one feels neutral feeling, one does not feel pleasant or painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: On that occasion, one feels only neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, so my interpretation is that, basically, it's highlighting... What comes first.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: The discontinuity of feeling as a container for your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, but... by regarding currently enduring feeling as that which is first,
[SPEAKER_01]: Means that's the entirety of your container, of your present experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether you are now having... remembering something from your past, planning for the future, that is done within the current enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that people's attitude towards their own feelings and perceptions, as I said, they put them second.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they don't recognize that... not just that there is a pleasant... like, if there is a pleasant feeling currently present, that's the only feeling you feel, as the Sutta says, but that's really... your entire existence is within that current feeling that endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the new feeling comes up, so to speak,
[SPEAKER_01]: When this feeling ceases, and next thing you know, now you're feeling unpleasant feeling, for whatever reason, when you become self-aware of it, you find it as already there, being felt, and you're within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no point in between one feeling, that then passes into next feeling, that then passes into next feeling, that then passes into next feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that point will require you to step outside of your experience as a whole, and observe that change from one, to two, to three.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you are within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you have is the enclosure of this kind, of this color, of this feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, within that, you're thinking, planning, acting, forgetting, greed, aversion, delusion, or sense restraint, virtue, all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh, now I find myself within another feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, how did that happen?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that becomes irrelevant question.
[SPEAKER_01]: It matters to somebody.
[SPEAKER_01]: How did feeling change from one to the other?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I observe the moment in between?
[SPEAKER_01]: A person who would be asking those questions is the person that refuses to give up the view, or is unable to give up the view, because he's not aware of it, of the external sense of self that observes this and that wants to monitor this change.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is what, like, sensuality, ill will...
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of these unwholesome states rely on that perversion of that same order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point here is then to recognize that, okay, so, I might really feel that it's important to find an answer how this feeling abruptly, now I feel this abruptly, now I feel neutral feeling abruptly, now it's pleasure abruptly, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does that change from one to the other?
[SPEAKER_01]: The pressure
[SPEAKER_01]: For that question, you need to basically subdue, and not waste your time trying to answer, because you're going to fall into speculative view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're very careful and transparent, you realize it's un... you'll be unable... you cannot possibly think outside of yourself, from which point you will have a neutral reference that tells you how one feeling for you, while it's being felt, becomes another.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize any notion of answering this requires the notion of that external world independent of my five aggregates, and that's fundamental wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of then trying to answer it, or trying to observe it through a meditation technique, like to narrow down the moments, it doesn't matter how closely you observe one moment to the next moment, the change between one to the next is always abrupt.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something you can see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were to see the change between moment A to moment B, well, there would be another moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, anything that you can observe is within that experience that already endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within that feeling, it's within that five aggregates, basically, that cannot be stepped outside of.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the practical point of that sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's exactly to recognize that it doesn't matter how specific the moment I'm observing might be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how, you know, pleasing and elaborate and satisfactory my explanation of the external process of change or flux can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, all of that is secondary to the presently enduring feeling, whichever that feeling is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about changing that feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about seeing how it changes from externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about not putting it second while it lasts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that he knows that in the current container of the experience as a whole, whereby a neutral feeling is currently present, that's the only feeling felt there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else is second to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And maintain that order, and then what then?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's next thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: What, what, what... Well, next thing is, when you exactly ask that question, what do I do next?
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, oh, is there another feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or it's still the same feeling that's present?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's still the same feeling, you include that question as second to that presently enduring feeling, and thus you don't lose the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you then find out yourself, oh, this is...
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel unpleasant now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of how did it come to be, and psychologists about it, you start recognizing, okay, that's the only feeling felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but that past feeling that I remember, it's now the memory, the perception, within this presently enduring unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there is no one container as a whole morphing into next one.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you have is one
[SPEAKER_01]: One, one, one.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, five aggregates, five aggregates, five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, in another words, as the sutra described, five aggregates are fading in, five aggregates fading away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fading in, fading away.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Coming and going, rising and falling, whichever way you describe it, on the level of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, like Buddha Vipassana, Digha Nikaya, he contemplated that.
[SPEAKER_01]: A rising and ceasing, rising and falling of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the complete liberation, for the complete arahantship and becoming sama-sambuddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you contemplate every single arisen experience as a whole, as a container in itself, that endures for as long as it wants to endure, so to speak, and any notion of sense of self, I am, conceit, present, future, loves, fears, worries, anything, any passion, greed, aversion, distraction, any hindrance you might have, you put that second within this presently enduring container,
[SPEAKER_01]: You do not pervert the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, the only possible result of that is dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, in the nutshell, that's exactly the practice of satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this sutta list mentions the three feelings as the point, but you realize you could practice exactly the same principle on the level of the body posture, or simply on the level of the body being there as a necessary container for any past, present, future memories, hindrances, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling perceptions, in the sense of states of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You perceive your states of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is my mood?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is my general mood?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it elated?
[SPEAKER_01]: Depressed?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of thinking like you are this entity that goes through these different moods, you recognize it's... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: These different moods keep containing this entity that I keep confusing it to be the same person, the same
[SPEAKER_01]: The same phenomenon that exists now, independent of these moods.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or dhammas, just in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: The four satipaṭṭhāna is just the dhammas.
[SPEAKER_01]: The actual phenomena, in that most precise phenomenological sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every presence of every thought, on that phenomenological basis, you realize that, well, that's a container in and of itself, for this whole experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what endures.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not the continuity.
[SPEAKER_03]: The sense of continuity...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense of continuity is second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And once you put it second, well, it ceases to be that continuous thing that exists outside of your sense of... of your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't...
[SPEAKER_03]: Choose not to have the sense of continuity.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the only way to uproot it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is to change the order.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: To say, like, I'm refusing to have this sense of continuity.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that sense of continuity, basically, is what it's kind of... would kind of remain to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when complete dispassion is developed, in the case of an arahant, that sense of continuity
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what's called pūgala, what's called individual, what's called basically the history of these five aggregates, the habits, the ways it was operating, that are now freed from greed, aversion, delusion, freed from these influxes of asavas and pollutions, but to some extent they remain standing there for as long as the five aggregates don't break apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that sense of continuity will not be confused for the sense of self, independent of the feeling, of the perception, of the mood, of the dhammas, of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will simply be, yeah, it's the same five aggregates that have been enduring for this long.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the non-persisting, world-changing in the Anguttara 347.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's, it's, yeah, but obviously it's impossible as a non-Arahant to, to like, yeah, imagine or conceive that, but it's... You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you're conceiving it, that's already a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, obviously, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to be conceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way is to... as I said, you won't provide, or you can try, but... and you can provide an answer, but it will never be accurate, because providing an answer requires that external point of view to what's happening here and now, moment to moment to moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And doesn't matter how hard you concentrate within moment to moment, you're still doing it internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still doing it as...
[SPEAKER_01]: As someone who is fully enclosed by each moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter how many moments you observed, you're equally enclosed within each and every one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every single time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you narrow in between the moments, well, that's another moment you're enclosed with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no way out through that concentrating techniques or obviously through like a speculative mystical experiences that take you outside of yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything you experience is on the basis of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter if it's unfamiliar, if it's unknown, it's still experience real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the recognition is then, is to discern rightly, with the right view, these correctly enduring reference points, body, feeling, moods, states of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's when you recognize that you don't get rid of the feeling, you don't get rid of the state of mind, you just see it for what it is to the extent that it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what satipaṭṭhāna describes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, he knows elated mind as elated mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent it... the mind is as such, he knows it as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows depressed mind as depressed mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He does not observe it or tries to psychologize it or find a way out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He simply knows it and that means he puts it in the right place.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows it as first and everything else, every pressure, any other hindrance they might want to make you doubt it, change it, do this, do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He puts that second within the enduring state of mind or within the enduring state of feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you could say the the essential difference is basically instead of seeing things or trying to see feeling as a thing that you can act towards or against,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically, like you said, to see it as being there beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before you even...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... Before you can even act towards it, or against it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a point also.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not be clear on the basis of what I said, but that's... yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you find yourself already feeling such and such feeling, that's... that's like... the key is to recognize there was no, like, first moment from which you saw that feeling start, because that implies you were there before the feeling, outside of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already find, whether it's the body posture, whether it's the feeling, whether it's the state of mind, mood, whether it's the dhammas, you find them as already there, given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've found them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recollected them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You brought them up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they were there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah!
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they did not originate from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not their creator.
[SPEAKER_01]: You find them, and then you act out of them, and by doing so, you appropriate them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You put yourself first, and by putting yourself first, you become the owner of these things, even pains and bad moods that you don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people like...
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't help but feel affected by the bad mood, the bad feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can't help but take it as yours, their own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't just say, oh, I won't take it as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because on other occasions, they keep taking it as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through perverting their road, that's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you would... you would not be observing that feeling, how it lasts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would simply find it there, know it as an enduring container, and your sense of self, that's... used to be regarded as the owner, as the one who acts, who sorts the feelings out, who... who manages them, this... all of that, you first restrain, in order to place it second within the enduring container of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: For how long you do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, for as long as that feeling... for until that feeling changes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that feeling changes, then you find yourself feeling another feeling, as the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you can feel is one feeling at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do you do then?
[SPEAKER_01]: You do the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, in... if it's the pleasant feeling that you're enduring, the leaning that you would have to be restraining and containing would be to prolong that pleasure to get more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's unpleasant feeling that you're enduring, the leaning that you would have to be restraining,
[SPEAKER_01]: The leaning that you would have to be restraining is aversion towards it, to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it's a neutral feeling that you're currently enclosed within, well, what you have to restrain is basically indolence, distraction, boredom, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that feeling for what it is, that neutrality, on account of what's being felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Could you describe those as, like, craving, aversion, distraction, as, like, trying to employ continuity, in a way?
[SPEAKER_03]: Trying to... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Continuity will pressure you, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, not continuity.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sense of ownership, the sense of self, the sense of craving, the habit of putting yourself first, the weight of that will pressure you, will want to maintain itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The momentum of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's kind of the... what you need to kind of work against.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when that weight disappears, then it becomes inconceivable to actually change the order, because you realize the order was never changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impermanence was always impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta was always anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unownership was always...
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that are unownable, they were unownable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was just you being completely deluded in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, employ continuity means cover up the factual discontinuity that is unavoidable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said initially, that the weight on that... on the sense of self being put first...
[SPEAKER_01]: That will pressure you, basically, to maintain it there, because it's going to feel unpleasantly, if you start shifting that weight away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, if sense of self, that's based on the sense of control and ownership, if you start contemplating non-control and non-ownership, well, that sense of self are going to resist.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to resist a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to... it's not going to take it lightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: In terms of establishing the right order, you get to... maybe you get the idea of what that is, that you are second to the container, you're within experience, confined.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you want to try to keep that vision, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, and the only way to see that, okay, sense restraint and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: It helps to clarify your situation, but Centrist in itself, being aware, being present, momentary, doesn't doesn't give you that right order, that vision, that right vision.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... No, because what you are present, moment to moment, is your perverted order.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't know the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know what comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practicing moment to moment awareness, or whatever they describe it these days,
[SPEAKER_01]: All you're practicing is moment-to-moment perversion of the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: It remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just be mindful of your... Of whatever's there and you don't even know where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why body, speech or mind... See, you can get the sense of the right order, like, through pondering, through reflecting and so on,
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're still perverting it through bodily actions, well, it's not gonna take root.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're perverting it through verbal actions, it's not gonna grow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're perverting it through mental actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And perverting it through body, speech or mind, it's exactly acting out of greed, aversion, delusion, conceit, hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it takes you away from that, from having perspective or... Well, because they, those, those phenomenon, phenomenon of greed, aversion, desire, sensuality, that is a phenomenon of perverted order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, choosing to act upon it is equals to choosing to pervert the order, even if you don't necessarily think in those terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's unwholesome, just in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will control these feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will produce these feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you might not even think those thoughts at all, but that's the implication.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, put yourself first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever there is a desire involved, ill-will, distraction, you put yourself first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can contemplate on top of it, the right order, all you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your actions are still putting yourself first, in that fundamental existential sense, well, as I said, the right order cannot possibly begin to grow, and everything else that would come from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, a person wants to put themselves second, in this right sense, and you have strong feelings of pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: And instead of trying to sort that pain out, you just put it, put yourself... Well, see, first you need to not act out of the pressure to sort the feeling out.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was like you have to, you have to let it endure for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not to say, oh, just endure it blindly like a fool and it will just, wisdom will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first you don't act out of it, it has to endure for what it is, so that you then see your aversion towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And put it second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you put it second, it's gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, gratuitous unnecessary...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, completely within the arisen feeling that's presently enduring, there is no outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you put your aversion second, the pressure to act out of that aversion dissipates, almost instantaneously.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the right order is established, even for a finger snap, as the suttas would say, for that finger snap, the liberation is felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point there is to then recognize that, okay, out of faith, initially, you don't act out of trying to sort out the unpleasant feeling and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize your aversion towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you basically include the aversion within the pain that endures and not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as I said, the pressure to act out will diminish.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, secondly, then you also get to recognize that that feeling that you found as already being there, arisen on its own, that's why it's going to go away on its own as well, without you needing to act out at all, out of anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the recognition of this manifested feeling becomes the... oh, its manifestation is its unmanifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to unmanifest because it's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever has manifested, that's why it has to unmanifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because it's like this, or like that, or I did this, or I said this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply because it is, it will not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that, in and of itself, liberates you from anything, everything, the whole saṃsāra, if it's fully developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Came on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Endures on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: No room for you there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the recognition of Sotāpanna, as we mentioned before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever has the nature to manifest, that's why it will unmanifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't need to wait for quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't wait for thing to end to see its unmanifestation or to see its impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you see it while the thing is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the recognition that manifestation, anything that's manifested in your experience, as a whole, on the level of the five aggregates, because it's manifested, that's why it has to unmanifest.
[SPEAKER_03]: Including the sense of continuity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Including any, any, doesn't matter, far, near, subtle, coarse, broad, general, particular, any phenomenon, to the extent that it's manifested, to the extent that it's present, that, that's why it will unmanifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And put that first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Put that container first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And protect it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't violate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't pervert it through your action by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in terms of...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, again, putting yourself second, container first, and trying to keep that right order.
[SPEAKER_02]: Trying to develop it, so that it takes root, or that it... everything flips, flips in the right way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Keep precepts, sense of strength.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, there's the other exercise of
[SPEAKER_02]: Wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Continuous wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Practice of wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as I said, you can't be wakeful and present and expect that to sort things out for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to keep awake and present with this right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the practice starts with knowing the right order, knowing the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know what the right order is, everything else you do is kind of circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not to say that you shouldn't keep the precepts if you're not a sotāpanna, but it's to say that you should recognize, that you ought to recognize that the practice begins with knowledge of the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: First is first, second is second, you know, turning the upside down.
[SPEAKER_02]: But anyone can practice wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anybody can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if people do that on the basis of knowing the right order, well, then they are actually progressing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If people keep... anybody can keep the precepts and practice sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: If people do that on the basis of the knowledge of the right order, well, that's pretty much the development of the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it, you know, you maintain wakefulness through the first watch of the night?
[SPEAKER_02]: Through the last watch of the night, so through the day, through the first watch of the night, and in the middle of the night, you go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_02]: You get up and do the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Purify the mind of obstacles.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: To what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what's an obstacle?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you got to know?
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to have... Just randomly, randomly purifying your mind from things you think they shouldn't be there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or are you purifying the mind from things that are trying to pervert the right order?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you removing the wrong order?
[SPEAKER_01]: You catch yourself putting yourself first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's an impurity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you remove that impurity by fixing the right order, by seeing what needs to be seen as first and seeing what needs to be seen as second.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, all those hindrances are things which pervert the order that you're trying to keep.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can... yeah, I was reading that, you know, wakefulness, you know, first watch of the night, don't go to sleep for as long as you can, go to sleep in the middle, wake up very early and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if someone takes it... And do it in and of itself, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: In and of itself, it can almost drive you mad, because... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you... What are you doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you doing it for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no, that's really like... the emphasis...
[SPEAKER_01]: The goal should be discernment of the right order, on the basis of virtue and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the sotāpārtha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you'll know what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will then also know how to protect that right order, and other things will fall into place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're just trying to do same, trying to do satipaṭṭhāna, ānāpānasati, that's why I keep saying it applies only to sotāpārthas or higher.
[SPEAKER_01]: You keep trying to do those things, thinking they, in and of itself, will result in this recognition of...
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to learn what recognitions you have to understand, what anicca is on that right level, and then it has to be endured there until it's kind of seen correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can even listen to this talk, read the suttas, get the sense of the right order and so on, but when, say, unpleasant feeling is present, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're craving in aversion to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you able to contain it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you able to put it second?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you able to then uphold the values of the right order and not act out of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: For months, if it takes that long for that feeling to dissipate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, by the end of the day, you have to act out, you have to say something, you have to address this, because it becomes too confining and you can't bear it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there is no right view being developed, because you keep puncturing the container, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: You keep letting the pressure out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you can't hold the pressure, well, you need to then build up the container to hold the pressure first.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's what I think, that's what I think that practice of weightlessness is doing, is maintain... Oh yeah, yeah, that will intensify, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maintain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's done on the basis of the gradual training, when it comes to do that, you will be able to intensify it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you just do it as, as I said, as some sort of practice, expecting that it will result in this release, it won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not of the release that matters, at least.
[SPEAKER_02]: Never distract yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Never give in to indolence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Never turn off that...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even just the fact that you're staying awake.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you've got the right order, you've got the idea of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that you're staying... you've made a determination to stay awake as long as you can, in the face of tiredness and so on, kind of reminds you of your determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, as I said, it is kind of pushing a bit further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Testing it, pressuring the upholding of the right order, so to drain away any impurities that might still be hiding there further, deep inside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because that indolence is that, or that wanting to look away from that pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, want to distract yourself, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very strong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just forget, forget about it for a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have a break from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, as I said, somebody in the beginning who doesn't have even the right view or who hasn't like cultivated it sufficiently enough, those things are too subtle to worry about them at that point.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, address the coarse impurities.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't start the suttas that describe purifying the gold.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't purify the gold by picking the microscopic bits out, but there's still like
[SPEAKER_01]: lumps of mud, you know, flowing around.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you get the obvious stuff first out, then the less obvious and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when there's nothing else, you get to see, oh, look, no, this is impurity and that.
[SPEAKER_01]: In this, you won't even see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just covered with all the other dirt.